Guide to the John Hope Franklin papers, 1891-2010, bulk 1950-2010 RL.10029
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Hope Franklin papers
1891-2010
1950-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Franklin, John Hope, 1915-2009
John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
RL.10029
306 Linear Feet
John Hope Franklin was a celebrated and pioneering historian specializing in Southern and African American history. The papers document his entire career as well as his personal life and political interests: his prolific writings on African American and Southern history; his role as a mentor and colleague; his role in associations such as Phi Beta Kappa, the American Historical Association, the Association for the Study of African American Life and History, and others; his participation in the civil rights movement, including his work with the NAACP Legal and Educational Defense Fund, the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, and Justice Thurgood Marshall; and his engagement with numerous civic, community, and educational organizations such as the Board of Foreign Scholarships and Fisk University's Board of Trustees. There is also a significant amount of material from Franklin's work on President Clinton's Advisory Board for the President's Initiative on Race in 1997 and 1998. Items in the collection include files of correspondence in original order; research sources and notes; writings by and about Franklin; materials relating to family history; papers and diaries of other family members, including his father, and wife, Aurelia; printed material; event folders; many informal and publicity photographs; video and sound recordings; and awards and other memorabilia. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture at Duke University.
Arrangement
Arranged in the following series: Academia; Advisory Board for the President's Initiative on Race; Audiovisual Materials; Correspondence; Engagements; Honors and Awards; Personal and Family Materials; Research, Biographical, and Subject Files; Service; Writings; and Writings by Others; and the Courtland Cox Papers.
Biographical note
John Hope Franklin was born on January 2, 1915, in Rentiesville, Oklahoma. He was the youngest of four children born to Buck Colbert Franklin, an attorney, and Mollie Parker Franklin, a teacher. In 1925, the family moved to Tulsa. Franklin graduated from Booker T. Washington High School in 1931, at age sixteen. He attended Nashville's Fisk University, where he received his B.A. in History in 1935. With the financial help of his undergraduate mentor, Professor Theodore S. Currier, Franklin continued his education at Harvard University, becoming the first African American graduate student in the Department of History. He received his M.A. in 1936 and completed his Ph.D. in 1941. During that time, Franklin taught briefly at Fisk University before accepting a position at St. Augustine's College in Raleigh, NC in 1939. In 1940, Franklin married his wife of fifty-nine years, Aurelia Whittington Franklin. The two had met as classmates at Fisk. Their son, John Whittington Franklin, was born in 1952.
In 1943, Franklin published his first book, The Free Negro in North Carolina, 1790-1860, and joined the History Department at the North Carolina College for Negroes in Durham (now North Carolina Central University). During his tenure there, he began research for From Slavery to Freedom: A History of American Negroes, a seminal text on African American history. The book was first published in 1947 and has remained in print since. That same year, Franklin received an appointment at Howard University in Washington, DC. It was in Washington that Franklin met prominent white historian, C. Vann Woodward. Soon after, the two integrated the 1949 meeting of the Southern Historical Association. While at Howard, Franklin joined other prominent historians and assisted the NAACP's Legal Defense Fund school desegregation case, Brown vs. Board of Education.
In 1956, Brooklyn College, a predominantly white institution, appointed Franklin as Chairman of the Department of History. Franklin made headlines as the first African American appointed chair in any department at a traditionally white institution. In the course of his tenure in Brooklyn, where he served until 1965, Franklin published three books: The Militant South, 1800-1860 (1956), Reconstruction after the Civil War (1961), and The Emancipation Proclamation (1963). He spent the 1963 school year as the Pitt Professor of American History at St. Johns College in Cambridge University.
In 1964, Franklin joined the faculty at the University of Chicago. He was the Chairman of the History Department from 1967 to 1970 and the John Matthews Manly Distinguished Service Professor from 1969 to 1982. While at the University of Chicago, Franklin served as the President of the Southern Historical Society, the Organization of American Historians, and the American Historical Association. In addition to leading prestigious scholarly organizations, Franklin also served on the National Council on the Humanities from 1976 to 1982, and published Color and Race (1969) and Racial Equality in America (1979). He became Professor Emeritus at UC in 1982.
Franklin and his wife Aurelia retired to North Carolina in 1981 where he served for one year as a fellow with the National Humanities Center in Research Triangle Park. In 1982, he joined Duke University's faculty as the James B. Duke Professor of History. He was the first African American to hold an endowed chair at Duke. Upon reaching the mandatory retirement age in 1985, he retired for a second time to Professor Emeritus in a History Department and became Professor of Legal History at Duke, a position he held until 1992. During that time, he published George Washington Williams: A Biography (1985) and Race and History, Selected Essays (1989).
During the 1990s, Franklin received numerous awards and honorary degrees in recognition of his groundbreaking scholarship, academic service, and dedication to teaching. In 1995, President William Clinton awarded him the Presidential Medal of Freedom. Clinton also appointed Franklin to chair the Advisory Board on the President's Initiative on Race from 1997 to 1998.
Well into his late 70s and 80s, Franklin continued his research and writing with The Color Line: Legacy for the Twenty-First Century (1993) and My Life and an Era: The Autobiography of Buck Colbert Franklin, which he edited with his son, John Whittington Franklin. Franklin published two more scholarly works with historian Loren Scwheninger, Runaway Slaves: Rebels on the Plantation (1999) and In Search of the Promised Land: a Slave Family in the Old South (2005). His last book was his own autobiography, Mirror to America: the Autobiography of John Hope Franklin, published in 2005.
Franklin died on March 25, 2009, in Durham, North Carolina. He was 94 years old.
Chronology
1915 Jan. 2 Born in Rentiesville, OK, to Buck Colbert and Mollie Franklin
1935 B.A. in History, Fisk University
1940, June 11 Married Aurelia E. Whittington, librarian
1939-1943 Appointed to the History faculty at St. Augustine's College, Raleigh, NC
1943-1947 Taught at NC College for Negroes (now NC Central University), Durham, NC
1941 Ph.D. in History, Harvard University
1947 Published seminal work, From Slavery to Freedom: A History of American Negroes
1947-1956 Taught at Howard University, Washington, DC
1951 Traveled to Austria as a lecturer for the summer Salzburg Seminar in American Studies; with Aurelia Franklin, visited other European cities as tourist
1952 Birth of John "Whit" Whittington Franklin
1954 Commissioned by Thurgood Marshall, then legal counselor for the NAACP, to research and write a series of articles for the upcoming Brown vs. Board of Education hearings
1956-1963 Taught at Brooklyn College and chaired the History Department
1960 Traveled to Australia on a Fulbright Award, lecturing on African American history and race relations in the U.S.
1962-1963 Taught at Cambridge University as the Pitt Professor of American History and Institutions
1964-1982 Taught at the University of Chicago
1983-1992 Joint appointment to the Duke University faculty History Department and Law School
1995 Awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom by President Bill Clinton
1997-1998 Chaired President Clinton's Advisory Board for the President's Initiative on Race (ABPIR)
2005 Published Mirror to America: The Autobiography of John Hope Franklin
2009 March 25 Died in Durham, NC
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research, although some portions of the Audiovisual and Writings series are restricted. Please see the series descriptions and detailed inventory for more specific information about restrictions.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Hope Franklin Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift between 1996 and 2019.
Collection Overview
The John Hope Franklin papers document the whole of Franklin's professional career as a historian, as well as his personal life, early student years, and political interests. Collection materials include correspondence, research materials assembled by Franklin, writings by and about Franklin, drafts of writings, materials relating to family history, printed material, notebooks, information and multimedia packets, clippings, photographs, video and sound recordings, as well as a few artifacts. The collection was acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Center for African and African American History and Culture.
The Academics series chronicles Franklin's career as a professor of history. It includes materials documenting his role as a mentor and advisor to numerous undergraduate and graduate students, his lecture notes and other classroom materials, and his administrative and committee work at various institutions, including Brooklyn College, University of Chicago, and Duke University. Portions of this series are restricted.
The series on the Advisory Board for the President's Initiative on Race contains items Franklin gathered during his work on President Clinton's race initiative, "One America in the 21st Century." The bulk of the series dates from the year-long work of the Advisory Board, from 1997 to 1998, and primarily comprises items sent to the Board for consideration in its work, meeting materials, publicity, and scholarly materials.
The videos and sound recordings in the Audiovisual series were created or assembled by John Hope Franklin. The series has been arranged into three subseries: ABPIR Materials, Recordings of Franklin, and Recordings of Others. Originals in the Audiovisual Materials Series are closed to use. Use copies are available for some items. Please contact Research Services staff in advance before coming to use this series.
The Correspondence series is one of the largest series in the collection, and comprises personal and professional correspondence received and sent by Franklin throughout his adult life.
The Engagements series includes invitations, correspondence, programs, and itineraries related to Franklin's participation in scholarly, civic, and social events. These materials have been arranged chronologically.
Franklin's Honors and Awards series includes certificates and diplomas, as well as logistical and administrative documentation for many of the awards ceremonies. The series is divided into Honorary Degrees and General Awards, both sorted in chronological order.
The Personal and Family Materials series contains the earliest items in the collection, with materials from Franklin's parents and grandparents. It includes files documenting Franklin's life and interests outside of his scholarship and public service. Materials are arranged by family member, with Franklin's wife, Aurelia, and his father, Buck Colbert Franklin, heavily represented. Also contains papers related to Theodore Currier, Franklin's mentor; John Hope eventually served as an executor of his estate.
The Research, Biographical, and Subject Files series contains newspaper clippings, subject files, travel guides, and photocopies of Franklin's FBI file. Also contains publicity and newspaper coverage of Franklin's many interviews and public appearances throughout the twentieth century.
The large Service series includes files acquired through Franklin's government, professional, and community service with various organizations and projects. Materials range from the early 1950s through the 2000s and are arranged alphabetically by organization or project name.
Franklin's prolific writing career is documented in the Writings series, which includes materials on his many books, articles, speeches, book reviews, essays, interviews, and other works, many unpublished. A portion of this series is restricted; please contact the Rubenstein Library for more information.
The Writings by Others series documents the ongoing relationship Franklin had with other authors and historians. It includes correspondence, drafts, and printed materials. Files are arranged alphabetically by author.
Finally, the Courtland Cox papers is a series of manuscripts belonging to Cox, a civil rights activist, collected by Franklin as supporting materials for a research project. The Rubenstein Library also holds a separate collection of Cox papers chiefly relating to his work with the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC).
African American authors; African American college teachers; African American historians; African Americans -- History -- Study and teaching; African Americans -- Intellectual life; African Americans -- Personal narratives; African Americans -- United States -- History; Historians -- Correspondence; Historians -- United States; Presidents -- United States -- Racial attitudes; Race riots -- Oklahoma -- Tulsa; Racism -- United States -- History; Segregation -- United States -- History; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Southern States -- History; United States -- Race relations; Audiovisual materials; Moving images; Color films (visual works); Digital audio formats; Digital moving image formats; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings; Brooklyn College. Dept. of History; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; President's Initiative on Race (U.S.). Advisory Board; Franklin, Aurelia Elizabeth; United States. Board of Foreign Scholarships; NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund; Fisk University. Board of Trustees; American Historical Association; Association for the Study of Afro-American Life and History; Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies (U.S.); University of Chicago. Dept. of History; Duke University. Department of History; Currier, Theodore S.; Franklin, John Hope, 1915-2009; Franklin, Buck Colbert, 1879-1960; Cox, Courtland, 1941-
- Academia (AC), 1931-2006; 10 boxes
  Arrangement
  The Academia series contains three subseries: Student Files, Lecture Notes, and Colleges and Universities. Student Files have been arranged alphabetically by student name. Lecture Notes are arranged alphabetically by title. Colleges and Universities have been sorted by college, reflecting Franklin's long career as an educator at institutions around the United States.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series chronicles Franklin's work as a professor of history. It includes materials documenting his role as a mentor and advisor to numerous undergraduate and graduate students, his lecture notes and other classroom materials, and his administrative and committee work at various institutions. Student Files make up a significant portion of the series. Franklin kept files on particular students, arranged by name, from Brooklyn College or the University of Chicago. Teaching Materials consists largely of general lecture notes from various courses Franklin taught through his career. The Colleges and Universities subseries has been arranged by school, with the majority of files stemming from Franklin's work at Brooklyn College, University of Cambridge, University of Chicago, and Duke University. This subseries includes materials relating to Franklin's appointments and employment as well as department and university-level correspondence, events, and committees.
  - Student Files, 1958-1990s
    Name files maintained by Franklin for select students (usually PhD students) at Brooklyn College and the University of Chicago. Typical files include dissertation abstracts, Franklin's evaluations of their work (not including grades), correspondence and letters of recommendation, and published articles or other clippings. These files often extend far beyond the dates of the students' enrollment in Franklin's departments, reflecting his continuing role as a mentor and colleague to many of his former PhD students. The Student Files subseries includes notable figures such as Genna Rae McNeil, Alfred Moss, and Loren Schweninger, each of whom went on to collaborate with Franklin on some of his later publications.
    - A-Har (Box AC1)
    - Har-Mo (Box AC2)
    - O-Wa (Box AC3)
  - Teaching and Lectures, 1940s-1980s and undated
    This subseries contains Franklin's lecture notes and some booklists for courses he taught on Southern history, Reconstruction, and African American history. Only a few are dated; it appears he used the majority of these notes repeatedly. Files are arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Andrew Jackson and the New Democracy, undated (Box AC4)
    - Andrew Jackson and Presidential Power, undated (Box AC4)
    - Antebellum South, 1980-1984 and undated (Box AC4)
    - Everlasting South, undated (Box AC4)
    - Expansionism and Sectionalism, undated (Box AC4)
    - Foreign Policy in the Making, undated (Box AC4)
    - Growth of American Civilization, 1980 (Box AC4)
    - History of the American Negro, 1958 (Box AC4)
    - History exam sample, undated (Box AC4)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated, 2 folders (Box AC4)
    - Negro Leadership in the United States, undated (Box AC4)
    - New South, undated (Box AC4)
    - Nineteenth Century - Years of Maturity, undated (Box AC4)
    - Post-War South, undated (Box AC4)
    - Reconstruction, undated (Box AC4)
    - Revolution of 1800, undated (Box AC4)
    - South Expansionists of 1846, 1959 and undated (Box AC4)
    - South in the New Nation, 1980 (Box AC4)
    - South in the 20th Century, 1979 and undated (Box AC4)
  - Colleges and Universities, 1931-2006
    Includes administrative files, committee meetings, correspondence, and other materials relating to Franklin's work as a professor in history departments throughout the United States. The majority of the subseries dates from Franklin's years at Brooklyn College, University of Cambridge, University of Chicago, and Duke University. Some material overlaps with the Student Files subseries. Also held in this subseries are materials from Franklin's earlier posts as a professor at St. Augustine College, North Carolina College, and Howard University, as well as files from several of Franklin's short-term visiting professorships. Materials from Duke University fall under Duke University Archives restrictions. Gradebooks from Franklin's early days of teaching and his card files of students at the University of Chicago are held in Box AC10. Grades are closed to researchers for the lifespan of the student.
    - Early Appointments and Visiting Professorships, 1931-1989
      - St. Augustine's College syllabi and student correspondence, 1931-1981 (Box AC4)
      - North Carolina College Visiting Professor, 1949 (Box AC4)
      - North Carolina College correspondence, 1960s-1990 (Box AC4)
      - Harvard University Visiting Professor, 1950 (Box AC4)
      - Howard University lecture notes, undated (Box AC4)
      - Howard University correspondence with students, 1960-1985 and undated (Box AC4)
      - Howard University correspondence re: administration, teaching, etc., 1948-1962 and undated (Box AC4)
      - Howard University administrative materials, 1949-1954 (Box AC4)
      - Howard University Committee on Intellectual Quality of Howard University Students report, undated (Box AC4)
      - University of Wisconsin Visiting Professor, 1953 (Box AC4)
      - University of California Visiting Professor, 1956 (Box AC4)
      - University of Hawaii Visiting Professor, 1959 (Box AC4)
      - University of Maryland Visiting Professor, 1964 (Box AC4)
      - Stanford Law School Visiting Professor, 1989, 2 folders (Box AC4)
      - Stanford University Law School, "The Law of Freedom and Bondage," 1988-1989 (Box AC4)
    - Brooklyn College, 1956-1980
      - Appointment congratulations, 1956-1957, 2 folders (Box AC4)
      - Faculty reports, undated (Box AC4)
      - Bulletin, 1962-1964 (Box AC4)
      - General student correspondence, 1959-1963 (Box AC4)
      - Research Assistant: Lane, Ann, 1962-1982 (Box AC4)
      - Faculty: Eisenstadt, Abraham, 1963-1981 (Box AC4)
      - Faculty: Giles, Mary Francis, 1962-1968 (Box AC4)
      - Faculty: James, Eric, 1960-1962 (Box AC4)
      - Faculty: Schlissel, Lillian, 1974-1975 (Box AC4)
      - Faculty: Smythe, Hugh, 1950-1971 (Box AC4)
      - Correspondence with President Harry Gideonse, 1960-1961 (Box AC5)
      - General faculty correspondence, 1958-1980 (Box AC5)
    - University of Cambridge, 1957-1964 (Box AC5)
      Franklin and his family spent the 1962-1963 academic year at St. John's College at the University of Cambridge, where Franklin served as the Pitt Professor of American History.
      - Correspondence with colleagues and regarding engagements, 1957-1964, 1981, and undated, 4 folders (Box AC5)
      - Teaching materials, 1962 and undated (Box AC5)
      - Conference brochures and trip itineraries, 1962-1963 and undated (Box AC5)
      - Financial statements and invoices, 1962-1963 and undated (Box AC5)
      - Memos and minutes from university committees, 1962-1963 (Box AC5)
      - Reports and directories, 1962-1963 (Box AC5)
    - University of Chicago, 1963-1985
      - Appointment, 1963-1964 (Box AC5)
      - Appointment congratulations, 1963-1964 (Box AC5)
      - Faculty reports, 1964-1980 (Box AC5)
      - Congratulatory correspondence re: becoming Chairman of the History Dept., 1967, 5 folders (Box AC5)
      - Scrapbook of congratulations re: becoming Chairman of the History Dept., 1967 (Box AC5)
      - Distinguished Service Professorship, 1969-1980 (Box AC5)
      - Dept. Chairman, 1967-1970 (Box AC5)
      - Dept. chairmanship, 1970-1979 (Box AC5)
      - Membership on department committees, 1968-1970s (Box AC5)
      - Committee on Minority Student Concerns, 1969-1979 (Box AC5)
      - Committee on African and African American Studies, 1967-1975 (Box AC5)
      - Education Dept., 1969-1975 (Box AC6)
      - Committee on Academic Appointments, 1968-1971 (Box AC6)
      - Committee on Policy and Planning, 1972-1973 (Box AC6)
      - Harris Committee, 1969-1975 (Box AC6)
      - History Dept. Student Council, 1969-1970 (Box AC6)
      - Grants from K. Montgomery, 1975-1978 (Box AC6)
      - Danforth Foundation Minority Fellowship Program, 1967-1982 and undated, 3 folders (Box AC6)
      - Departed faculty: Johnson, Walter, 1963-1985 (Box AC6)
      - Departed faculty, 1973-1982 (Box AC6)
      - Visiting professors, 1962-1982 (Box AC6)
      - Faculty and colleagues, 1960s-1980s (Box AC6)
      - Student unrest, 1969-1970 (Box AC6)